# KAMRAN SALEEM

# **FINANCE & ACCOUNTS**

Email: <u>kamran238a@yahoo.com</u> Phone: +92- 305-4705986 Linkedin: linkedin.com/in/kamran-saleem1

Lahore, Pakistan



# **SUMMARY**

24+ years of experience in the Finance & Accounting sector, with expertise in Financial Statements, Budgeting & Forecasting, Financial Planning & Analysis, Profit & Loss Statements, Funds Allocation and Accounting Strategies. Experience in recording detailed accounting information for large organizations. Extensive knowledge of accounting software and processes with adeptness in maintaining deadlines and targets.

# PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

Accounts Management Budgeting & Forecasting Portfolio Management Tax Management Financial Management
Planning & Analysis
Financial Auditing
Compliance

Investment Management
Variance Analyses
Business Strategy
Corporate Finance

Financial Statements Process Improvement Fixed Assets/Capex Trade Finance

Dec 2019 till date

### **WORK HISTORY**

### PUNJAB GROUP OF COLLEGES, Lahore, Pakistan

#### **Accounts & Finance Manager**

The group is a leader in academic excellence, mass media communication and real-estate, among many other business ventures. Our real-estate projects, Union Developers - Etihad Town and Country Developers, are on a mission to transform the real-estate sector of Pakistan.

- Handling the finance and accounts of the real estate business projects of the company along with a team of 15 members.
- Recommend the corporate economic model for planning, forecasting and consequence analysis.
- Assess economic and financial risks to proposed future strategy, capex or financing proposals.
- Utilize analytics tools and developed models that support data-driven decision-making.
- Oversee the financial planning and operations of region and ensure the implementation of short-term & long-term strategic policies designed to grow the business.
- Forecast monthly, quarterly and annual revenue, margins and income projections for the region.
- Evaluate the company's performance for management review, including Gross Profit and Net Profits/Margins.
- Review key financial and operational business metrics, including sales and distribution revenue and margins.
- Responsible for financial statements including General Ledger, Profit & Loss Accounts, Age-wise Accounts Payables,
   Receivables Statements and Income Statement and Planning for the business.
- Oversee cost accounting, cash management, metrics analysis, taxations and financial reporting.
- Reconciliation of company's assets, liabilities, revenues, operating expenses, provisions, accruals entries and accounts.
- Produce monthly variance reporting, clearly articulating the linkage between operational and financial performance.
- Accountable for performing treasury functions such as capital management, daily liquidity, allocating cash balances, preparing forecasts, investment records, etc.
- Responsible for scrutinising credits, business service charges and other incomes.
- Preparation of MIS report of monthly sales, pending invoice certification, remittance pending, bank reconciliation, etc.
- Monitor client details for non-payments, delayed payments and follow-up for overdue collection by sending bill reminders.
- Provide coaching, direction and leadership to team members in order to achieve optimum business results.

### ALDAR PROPERTIES PJSC, Abu Dhabi, UAE

Aug 2007 – Jun 2017

### **Manager-Finance**

- Handled accounts of prestigious developments such as Ferrari World, IKEA, YAS Mall, Yas Marina Circuit (Formula 1 racing track), Al Raha Beach, National Housing Projects, World Trade Centre Abu Dhabi, Alpha Kazakhstan, etc.
- Reported to the Corporate Financial Controller and was accountable for the accuracy of financial transactions, Balance sheets, General Ledger, fixed assets, cash control, tax billing and collections.
- Collaborated with the project delivery team for project development, budgets, contractor payments and approvals.

- Prepared the annual budget and consolidation of the individual project budgets in partnership with the project delivery team and consultants.
- Provided information for the payments made against each contract / consultants, pending payments, schedule of payment cycle, etc. along with the project delivery team and the consultants for the twelve months rolling cash flow.
- Responsible for accuracy of company funds including bank deposits and internal cash funds, and monitored the income and expenses to determine cost cutting for maximizing profits.
- Supported in the area of budget preparation, forecasting budget control and analysis, financial reporting and accounting, direct reimbursements, etc. Validated budgeted cost from estimation team and compared it with actual cost incurred.
- Warranted the timely and accurate availability of information for the monthly management reports and audits.
- Accounted and maintained separate books of accounts for all transactions and handled submission of supporting schedules
  to auditors for yearly audits.
- Met with the project development team on regular basis to discuss the status on the development, review the cost reports to ensure that the cost incurred are properly considered in the cost reports.
- Generated daily invoices, billings and customer statements for customers and ensured that the invoices generated are posted to the Revenue and to the correct Customer accounts.
- Monthly analysis of various accounts as required in financial reports. Compiled financial statements and generated balance sheets and profit/loss statements.
- Calculated of retention values, advance payments, reduction, etc., and handled monthly payroll calculation, leave salary calculation and WPS.
- Safeguarded the company's interest from parallel business and revenue leakages. Ensured financial data confidentiality and conduct database backups. Monitored economic and financial market trends in order to stay ahead of the competition.

#### **Joint Ventures:**

- Responsible for setting up the accounting system in Oracle R12, including chart of accounts for all projects/customers
- Managed Ferrari Outlets in GCC in conjunction with their accounting function.
- Handled projects with Torex Software for Fadar Retail LLC (Ferrari stores in UAE, Saudi Arabia and Bahrain).

#### Other Employment Experiences (Pakistan)

Japan Power Generation Ltd.Manager- Finance & AccountsMar 2006- Jul 2007Service Sales CorporationManager- AccountsJan 2001- Feb 2006Irfan Textiles (Pvt) Ltd.Assistant Manager- AccountsJul 1998- Dec 2000

## **ACHIEVEMENTS**

- Set up and executed a Financial Software System (PHP-Java Scripting) for the Real Estate department within 3 months Punjab Group of Colleges.
- Collected an amount of USD 50 million for plot sales within 6 months for Punjab Group of Colleges.
- Management appreciation for outstanding performance and received highest bonus till date at Punjab Group of Colleges.
- Cost saving of USD 2.75 million on consultant cost for the project of WTC- Abu Dhabi for Aldar Properties.
- Cost saving of USD 4.1 million on contractor cost for the project of National Housing project- Alfalah for Aldar Properties.

# **QUALIFICATIONS**

2006: Masters in Business Administration (Finance) National College of Business Administration & Economics, Pakistan

1997: Chartered Accountancy (Finalist) Institute of Chartered Accountants, Pakistan

1993: Bachelors in Commerce (Accounting) Punjab University, Pakistan

## **TRAININGS**

- IFRS Review Training with Ernst & Young, Dubai.
- Workshop on Sales Tax & Income Tax conducted at LUMS under the presence of Federal Tax Ombudsman (FTO).
- Workshop on Income Tax conducted by NIU.

# **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Oracle 11i Oracle R12 Financials MS Office